[SPEAKER_01]: So, I thought to talk about... You know how the suttas often say, established in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's even like, kind of almost just synonymously with getting the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be like, you know, that sutta where a monk wanted to go in solitude, and the Buddha... and then, well, the Buddha told him not to, he ignored him, went there,
[SPEAKER_01]: He had a hard time, couldn't control his mind, came back and said that to the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha said, well, indeed, for as long as one is not established in virtue, or has jhāna properly, like the mind of jhāna developed, or has a right view, it's to be expected then that the thoughts of sensuality will overwhelm him in solitude and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess the question is, how one gets established in virtue?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it enough to just keep the precepts or would just keeping the precepts automatically or eventually result in establishment in virtue?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is, as I said, virtually like getting the right view.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're saying that if you just keep...
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't kill anyone.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't steal.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, just keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody's just keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that mean they're established in virtue?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do you need to do something more?
[SPEAKER_02]: Reflect on why the value of the precepts of virtue and the danger of
[SPEAKER_02]: Of not keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'm sure people who just keep the precepts do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that they don't think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is that... would that be enough to be established?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that... is that enough to become a sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_01]: With the right instruction and... Again, eh... they hear the right instruction, on account of which they keep the precepts and reflect upon their intentions,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, is that enough for satipaṭṭhā?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that enough to be close to the mind of jhāna and ready for the solitude and overcome everything else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, like you have... Or is something else missing?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you have to understand what virtue is, what non-virtue is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Meaning, you have to... You can say, I don't...
[SPEAKER_03]: I won't kill anyone, but, you know, why would I kill anyone?
[SPEAKER_03]: What, what are the qualities that would make me kill you?
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, remove those qualities, which could be, you know, for example, anger, anger towards, resistance towards painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if I remove that, that craving, then I cannot kill anyone.
[SPEAKER_03]: I cannot break any precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, by removing that craving, then I'm established in virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because I don't have a basis for non-virtue.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: What was that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so it's not about the rules of the precepts specifically, but about, well, understanding
[SPEAKER_00]: Why he... why they are always wrong, basically, and what would... Is there a simpler way of answering this question?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, like, we understand... understanding the value and why, but, say, somebody who is not as familiar with all these kind of jargon, so to speak, is there a way of development that they can do, that would result in establishment of virtue?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's... it's the precepts that you start with, but what else is lacking in regard to those precepts for somebody who is keeping them, but is not established in virtue?
[SPEAKER_01]: And they can be keeping them for 50 years, but still not be established in that virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, like, we can even think in terms of the
[SPEAKER_01]: The faith type, you know, the one that does not necessarily have a vast amount of information on the knowledge of the suttas, but has his confidence established in the right instruction, that leads from merely keeping the precepts all the way to arahanty.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that same thread that he has grasped,
[SPEAKER_01]: And has enough confidence to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is that threat?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is that that he would need to do?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, keeping the precepts is obviously not enough on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: What else?
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, within the same framework, what do they need to do?
[SPEAKER_03]: Not act out of craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what I said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can't just not act out of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the full understanding of craving, it's sort of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Feeds not acting out and not acting out, but it takes time to get there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So... Not distracting yourself, but that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: In a way, yeah, that's closer now to the to the to what I'm what I'm aiming at.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it self-reflection in the sense that... Again, that can be... Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, the term self-reflection can mean anything for anybody, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can take that to mean re-evaluating themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: But just like, on the basis of precepts, what do people not do?
[SPEAKER_01]: Even when they keep the precepts, where do they... what do they lack?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where do they stop short?
[SPEAKER_01]: Thinking why they're doing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: They might think why they're doing it, but still won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, let's start with this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the... What do the precepts apply to?
[SPEAKER_01]: What are they supposed to purify?
[SPEAKER_01]: Precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: The intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: More coarsely than that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Harming yourself and others.
[SPEAKER_03]: Bodily behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bodily behavior, yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you start with the bodily behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, again, just we're keeping it very simple.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not asking for, like, abstract, complex answers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just somebody who heard the Buddha once, and, uh-huh, I can do that, and did it, and became an arahant, without any other instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they would start, okay, precepts,
[SPEAKER_01]: Are the kind of a coarse container... well, container for the coarse bodily misbehavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you contain that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And do they need to stay there, that container?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can that container be taken further?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have body.
[SPEAKER_01]: What else you have?
[SPEAKER_01]: Speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the main reason, then,
[SPEAKER_01]: that somebody is not established in the precepts is because they have not applied them on these three levels.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the same way you're restraining your bodily behavior, you need to restrain your speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no other information or reasoning necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, in the same way you restrain your body and your speech, you need to restrain your mental images.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which ones you revolve around.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, oh, yeah,
[SPEAKER_01]: Most people don't do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even people that, as I say, can keep the precepts for hundreds of years, you realize, you never hear the part about restraining your mind on that right level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you might hear about concentrate on this, and when this is present, you do that, but all of those are actions and reactions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just in the same way, you abstain from intentionally giving in to certain bodily behavior,
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same way, you abstain from giving in to certain verbal behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's exactly the same thing that you're doing, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's something that people might not see, because they might say in theory, okay, yes, I need to be purified in my mind as well, but they might think that that is something different than the bodily and verbal behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why they would remain keeping the precepts for decades and not become established in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because... but it's in the same suttas that talk about keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: It carries on talking about how to then keep the speech and keep the mind, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's laid out in the same manner, in the same suttas, in the same way, but it's somehow...
[SPEAKER_01]: There is that kind of, okay, no, this applies up to here, and the rest of this, okay, speech, yes, people can see there is some input of their own, but when it comes to mind, oh, that will somehow magically happen on account of this practice or that practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you realize, no, no, no, you are fully responsible.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you have images of sensuality, as I said, well, you know, you can try to deny them, and distract yourself from it, and replace that experience with another, but there is no, there is no restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's certainly no understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you could, if you have such images, or images of ill-will, it's probably even more easier to relate for people.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're annoyed by somebody, by a person specifically, you're gonna have images of them, of that experience, of what you should have... all of these images that revolve around that experience, you're gonna have your mind have them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you are the one who then chooses to, as I said before, rest on those images and allow them to then perpetuate themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to fight them.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to try and get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you certainly need to not give them your wrong attention in that manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't allow your mind to rest on them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And don't lose the reference point in regard to those images.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you restrain your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, restraining the mind in regard to the unsuitable images, it's not on the level of trying to get rid of the images, or not have them arise in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the level of learning how to not give them the wrong attention.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not have them at center stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, not have them in in the center, basically, that then kind of makes the whole thing revolve around it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's, again, that is on the basis of the intentional effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, you see, even that is so invisible to people that they would think, also, I need to practice this moment-to-moment concentration to catch these little moments in between these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not where these things are.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you have been restraining your body, in other words, restraining the coarse outlets towards sensuality, ill-will and other unwholesome things, then, on top of that, you restrain your speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there are, again, many instances in the suttas
[SPEAKER_01]: Eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: What type of speech you should... speech you should not be engaging in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, again, that's on the basis of the intentional effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: You intentionally not allow yourself to become established on, like, in the experience of bad speech, in regard to this, in regard to that, in regard to gossip, malice, careless chatter, all of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you get... No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, I don't have to get rid of the intention or having to feel guilty for doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you catch it on that level, that's when you stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you realize that it's... it's on the basis of your choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the same leads to the choice on that mental... in regard to the mental images.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they present themselves, you realize you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Will I continue to give them the center stage, and then divorce myself from the experience of here and now, and whatever else I was doing, and let my mind kind of run with it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or will I say, no, I will not allow that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let them be there, but I will not allow my mind to focus on them fully.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that is a choice.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, obviously, we've all heard that sutta which says, you know, he destroys those thoughts, he obliterates them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: He smashes them out of existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then he describes how.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you smash them out of existence?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you get rid of them?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you destroy those thoughts?
[SPEAKER_00]: By not thinking out of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: By practicing yoniso manasikāra in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: The suttas very clearly say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the
[SPEAKER_01]: Properly attended thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you see, in order to attend something properly or improperly, it needs to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, these thoughts are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the question is not not having those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: The question is, oh, not attending to them mistakenly or, uh, unconcurrently, inconcurrently, how I say, but to attend to them rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all you need to do in regard to sweeping the leaves and having the thoughts of ill-will
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, I'll focus hard on the moments and sensations of leaves, so these thoughts don't bother me, nor is it, I'll forget about sweeping the leaves, or I'll even stop sweeping the leaves, and I'll just resolve this in my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically recognizing that both are there, simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have thoughts of your will, images associated with the person that upset you, and you do have recognition of what you're doing here and now through your other senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: Establishing that balance between the two is enough to not wrongly attend to ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's enough to not wrongly attend to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's enough to not wrongly attend to any hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And once that becomes more palpable, you realize, oh, yeah, I obliterate them by not giving, by not feeding them to wrong acknowledgement and mistaken attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the recognition of the, like, simultaneous two domains enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: You sweeping the leaves, talking here, and mind thinking certain thoughts at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not denying it, but you're certainly not forgetting which... where you are on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, I mean, a good point as well is that it's... it's important to realize that you can
[SPEAKER_00]: If you are, like, afraid of having such thoughts, or even, you know, seeing yourself having such thoughts, you don't want to kind of admit them to yourself or something, you don't want to be having those thoughts, that in itself will make it hard to actually correctly attend them, because you will be, like, trying to... by trying to ignore them,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a wrong way of attending them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're giving them that wrong attention.
[SPEAKER_00]: And actually, that's allowing them to proliferate there in the background, just ignoring them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's really the root of all unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the presence of those images, in regard to sensuality, or images in regard to your will, or in regard to worry, that's not the root of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's in those numerous suttas in the Guttara Nikaya, where the Buddha said, there is not a single thing such as
[SPEAKER_01]: ayoniso manasikāra, the incoherent intention, that makes unwholesome things increase, wholesome decrease, and unreasonably unwholesome to arise.
[SPEAKER_01]: And consequently, there's not a single thing that makes unwholesome things decrease and wholesome increase, such as yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is the root of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh... and that's exactly how one becomes established in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize, by practicing the same,
[SPEAKER_01]: Restraint in regard to the body, the speech, and the mind on the right mental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, okay, so restraint on the mind is not just denial of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just deny things to arise, to not arise, because you realize, well, that's not even the restraint on the level of the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: The restraint on the level of the body is not acting out towards possibilities that remain there in the world, but you choose to abstain from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, your abstaining, your sensory strength, exists concurrently with those possibilities.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neither are excluded.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just choose to maintain this, in regard to that, that is still present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very much so.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same with speech, and then you recognize, oh, so it's exactly the same principle with the mind, which is why, as I said, in the suttas, the whole thing is often bundled together.
[SPEAKER_01]: The same purification.
[SPEAKER_01]: It does not change or skip a beat and become something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's exactly the same development all the way through.
[SPEAKER_01]: But yes, that mental level needs to be discerned, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, recognizing images associated with centrality, images associated with
[SPEAKER_01]: With your will, with any hindrance.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, okay, so I don't try to get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know that they're there, but I do not allow them to become, as I said, the center of my focus, either through trying to get rid of them, fear them, act out of them, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole mindfulness of the body that gets developed, eh... because that's what's always concurrently present with... regardless of what state of mind you're in.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have your body there enduring simultaneously to that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that doesn't change, cannot change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being fully aware of them is not awareness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's absorption.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be fully absorbed in them, but then you're not aware of yourself or anything else in your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, you can be, like, half aware of something there, but trying to kind of ignore it and pretend it's not there, and, like, focus on the leaves and everything else that you're doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, equally, you're not... you're not actually properly aware of the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're trying to ignore it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereas,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because these things can really only operate where there's kind of a degree of ignorance, a degree of, like, ignoring it, ignoring one end of your experience at the expense of the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I mean, I'm just saying that because, like, the concurrency and so on can sound a bit...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that deliberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it boils down...
[SPEAKER_01]: To the very deliberation aspect of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just that, obviously, you need to first restrain other, more coarser forms of deliberation.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, once you start to recognize that allowing those images to take the center stage of your experience, it's an act, it's a deliberate act.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, oh, I need to restrain that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, I agree.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, whether we talk about intention or concurrency, all of these are kind of an indirect ways of pointing at there is an act of deliberation, either towards I want to get rid of these thoughts, again, it's a deliberate kind of denial, or I'll deliberately give in to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just... they're pressuring me.
[SPEAKER_01]: These images are just taking up all of my attention span, and there is always a point where you choose to give in to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, oh, that's what you need to not do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, just don't give in to that last drop.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can have all those images all you want, but if you don't allow that last...
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, I will allow them to take the center stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are in the clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you sustain that last not giving in on that mental level, the establishment of virtue, in virtue, is taking place.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, exactly, that comes down to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, so yes, you are actually addressing things in the root.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, the future bodily misbehavior or verbal misbehavior will be even less likely, if already on that mental level, you're recognizing that deliberate act of allowing these things, giving in, and you're not doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You let them be, but you don't do just that last last drop.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what the suttas would be describing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, he doesn't welcome these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, they're there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a question of getting rid of them.
[SPEAKER_01]: The question is of not welcoming them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you have even thoughts of ill will, that are unpleasant, you do welcome them, to then try to resolve it or act out and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is that... it feels that it's almost like, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not subconscious, but it kind of feels like an unconscious habit of... you just can't help but welcome first, and then try to resolve it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the reason why you can't help but welcome first, mentally, is because physically you still have not been thoroughly developed in that uprooting those wrong types of deliberate acts, nor verbally.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have not allowed those things to come up closer to the mental level, whereby the mental deliberation would become more obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you do always see that, as I said, like, you can be dwelling physically restrained, but then, something that's not necessarily unwholesome, like, and you kind of know that in and of itself, and nobody will be upset, but you know that it's rooted in desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or you know that in you, oh, this is rooted in ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is not a technical prohibition against saying something, but, again, you know that you are doing it out of your will.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you deliberately, then, choose to act out of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You deliberately choose to ignore the fact that, yeah, I know it's technically nothing wrong, but I'm not here to deal with technicalities, I'm here to uproot suffering and free myself from craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize also, then, there is no excuse, there is no exception.
[SPEAKER_01]: If things are rooted in obvious unwholesome states of mind, I should not say them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter what happens to the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you've been practicing that long enough, you will get to recognize that even before it comes to, like, speech and pertaining to speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will recognize those types of same deliberations and allowances and welcoming and accepting and turning a blind eye on that mental level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also, it relates to what you were saying about it being equivalent to the right, getting the right view, because it also relates to how the suttas describe it as becoming independent of others, in the sense of not being able to put any
[SPEAKER_00]: The thing that others might say, or no matter how much the world sort of says that this is okay, no matter how many other people who are all, you know, I respect them and everything, and they all do it, so it must be fine, or whatever other kind of notion or relying on others to some extent, it can't, kind of,
[SPEAKER_00]: Get prioritized above what you know your intention is rooted in, because you always know that you can't... you can deny it, you can cover it up with other things, but fundamentally, if you look, it's always... your intentions will tell you what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that has to be... that just has to be discerned.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, then you could also see how getting the right view is not an accident.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like a...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a lucky kind of experience that somebody just stumbles upon.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's just you go in this direction of development and established in virtue equals right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you realize then a person could, out of faith, take on the precepts,
[SPEAKER_01]: Learn about what's wholesome, what's unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Abstain from unwholesome physically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when the mind, when the mentally, mind starts to pressure them, and they start, you know, they might not be acting out physically, but they want to act out verbally, or distract themselves verbally, and start engaging in all this, then they restrain that.
[SPEAKER_01]: They recognize, okay, no, I will not give in to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Regardless of whether it's acceptable or not, I know that it's rooted in the same type of pressure that I'm restraining in regard to bodily behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if they haven't been acting out of speech, then either... Again, it's like, obviously depends on individual, but it won't be before long.
[SPEAKER_01]: If this is done rightly, you will get to then see the same pressure on the mental level.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, you're not acting by the body, you're not acting by the speech, but are you acting by the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you acting out?
[SPEAKER_01]: And as we described, acting out by the mind incurs a certain, that degree of
[SPEAKER_01]: Losing self-awareness in regard to your own thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Choosing to deliberately allow them to take the center stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not your self-awareness in regard to the thoughts, the concurrency of it, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even, as I said, without going into the simultaneity and the principle behind, just as a mere practice, you're like, okay, so I will not deliberately allow my attention to rest upon thoughts of sensuality when they come up and start pressuring me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Images.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not deliberately allow to rest my attention, myself, my experience as a whole, on the images of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can be there, but I won't get that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't, like, take them and put them in front of me, whereby, you know, everything else is going to start revolving around them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's how you don't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, when there is a
[SPEAKER_01]: A possibility to act out with your body in an unwholesome manner.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't go and destroy the tempting thing and kill people that might excite you or irritate you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, I'll have to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how I free myself from the world.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, oh, so you can't do...
[SPEAKER_01]: The same applies to the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just, oh, I'll get rid of these thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll forget about them.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll focus on something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, yeah, but again,
[SPEAKER_01]: The same principle remains.
[SPEAKER_01]: You still... the root of the problem is not having those thoughts in the first place.
[SPEAKER_01]: The root is that you cannot not allow them, deliberately, to take the center stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the training is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the thoughts are present, I must have to recognize that deliberate act of allowing them to to become sort of established in this center experience, and then everything I else... everything else I do becomes rooted in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, abstaining from that last allowance, that last welcoming, which is, as I said, a deliberate act.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it feels like automatic and subconscious, it's only because you haven't developed your behavior sufficiently in those more coarse manners.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you, through your act or through your reasoning, are you putting or implying the blame to be in those images or in you wrongly attending to them?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the key here.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, if you're denying it, if you're using meditation concentration technique, if you're doing this in response to that, that implication is always going to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think those images are the problem, and that's why you don't see the root of the problem, and that's why you won't be free in regard to it, and that's why you won't be established in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's you attending to them wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, you letting them take the center stage is the wrong attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, abstaining from that deliberate act, you are purifying way of attending to things, right?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a separate mystical practice, or I gotta practice yoniso and then apply it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not allowing them to take the center stage, which is a deliberate act, however subtle it might be, is your yoniso manasikāra practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a question of focus, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: The question is more of a deliberate degree of unfocus in regard to things you should be unfocused from.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the focus is... you're being pressured to focus.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're being pressured to give in and welcome this and accept it and then deal with it, either through denial or indulgence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But first and foremost, it's like that pressure to take me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, no, that's, that's the root of unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Me, taking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not this thing being there or pressuring me either.
[SPEAKER_02]: And the breath is there regardless of whether you attend to it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, everything is there regardless of whether you're attending or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the five aggregates, the body, the four postures, the breath, whichever basis for your mindfulness you want to take.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's also why it equals, like, well, sort of safety, sense of
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense of safety, in terms of it being something that can only ever be... it's totally in your hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, nothing can... no amount of images that come up.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your view, to some degree, implies that the problem is in those images, you can never feel safe, because it's always possible that some image can come up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you have absolutely nothing to bring those images up.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no way to hide from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter what you can do, it can still...
[SPEAKER_00]: It still might be possible that this might arise and there's no way of knowing or being sure that this can never arise again.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, so, like, to the extent that you have some kind of notion, or fear, or way, what if this comes up, or what if that comes up, you can sort of know that your... your virtue is not completely established.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it were, virtue that is... being established in virtue means recognizing virtue as something that no... nothing can...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's coming between you and...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's coming between you and it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is... it is always in your hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, as I said, for most people, it's too subtle, because they haven't been practicing sensory strain properly with the body, nor with the speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this feels like too subtle to notice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And thus, when you say you should not welcome these thoughts, for people that equals, I must get rid of those thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not the same statement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you... if you look at your intentions on the level of body and the speech, and, as I said, not act out of them, and then endure the mental pressure and state in regard to it, this deliberate act of accepting images on that subtle level will become apparent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Somebody said something upsetting.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is a pressure, there is an influx of images that are associated with that person in a... like a manner of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_01]: While I'm sitting here talking to you, I could choose now
[SPEAKER_01]: To withdraw my attention from sitting and talking to you, and allow these thoughts to take the center stage, and start to revolve, and feed, and this and that, and I should have said, I will say next time...
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, I was like, no, I'll let that domain, that entire domain of the mind that revolves around these images, I'll let it be there, but I will not allow it to deliberately take over me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just that last drop.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, oh, it's a restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's exact same principle of restraining the body, restraining the speech, I'm restraining the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Restraining the mind means not allowing your mind to take over you, whereby you lose your self-awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does not mean denying my mind, denying these thoughts, trying to get rid of them, trying to counter them or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't do that in regard to things that tempt you by the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not countering them constantly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, if you see something beautiful, you go and destroy it and make it ugly.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, restraining your mind means restraining, basically, the images when they present themselves from
[SPEAKER_01]: Overwhelming you, in a sense of making you lose self-awareness and making you basically allow them, accept them as the center stage of your efforts and acts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where that whole kind of the necessity of purifying your bodily behavior first, it's not optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you're still giving in by the body,
[SPEAKER_01]: All these things will remain abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be too subtle to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because even the bodily intention, of its course, nature, you still give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means you still imply, basically, that the problem is in things that tempted you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you give in to them, or you act out of them with anger, or whichever way.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so that needs to be contained first.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, on the subtler level, speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things you say, things you want to say, pressure to say, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it rooted in the pressure?
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't say.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll say everything else, if I have to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I won't say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not deliberately accept it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what if it stays there for like six months, pressuring me?
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter if it stays for 60 months, 60 years, six eons.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't say it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't accept that to be...
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't accept that act.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't accept those images.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's usually why people give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: What if this lasts forever?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, that's the training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressuring images, they want you to accept them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you don't accept them, they're going to obviously pressure you more to accept them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they can't do anything else to you, except trying to pressure you into accepting them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as you might feel like scared and overwhelming initially, but you know, well, that is the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else that follows, all this... all the things that I've previously restrained, all the unwholesome, was all just the result of this accepting images of the unwholesome nature, deliberately allowing them to take the center stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I never do that, I don't have to worry about anything else at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if those images...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if they keep coming, as I said, for next 60 years, you realize, well, not accepting them, it's kind of effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to go anywhere, climb the mountains.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Accept mentally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not accept them deliberately and allow them to take the center stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all I need to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it is peaceful.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not a fight.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not a...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's... exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: A task.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize why it would result in the equanimity, completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, there will be no room for ill will, nor any room for sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was gonna say, like, you realize that kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: Fearing, what if this pressure keeps pressuring me for whatever... That's actually, that's the, that's why it's pressuring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not, it's not, it's not it that is pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you kind of stop fearing it pressuring you, and you just say, well, yeah, you can keep for however long it takes, infinite, infinitely, like infinite, infinitely patient, I suppose, in regards.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no room for any pressure there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're infinitely patient, there's... that's almost like the definition of just something that's not bothering you at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Developing patience in regard to the right things.
[SPEAKER_01]: People can develop patience in regard to things that do not necessarily... that still imply the wrong view, that still imply that the problem is in the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when it comes to this true restraint, true physical restraint, verbal restraint,
[SPEAKER_01]: Once you recognize the deliberate acceptance of unwholesome thoughts on the mental level, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I develop patience in regard to that, then, yeah, that's pretty much the root of the development.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is like the the true kind of patient endurance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, patient endurance has to be exercised in regard to the body when you're pressured to act, in regard to the verbal when you're pressured to act, but the root of it is patient endurance in regard to the images associated with unwholesome,
[SPEAKER_01]: They want me to accept them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They want me to deliberately allow them, welcome them, to take the center stage.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, even if I then practice mindfulness and read the suttas and do all of this, all of that I do in response.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that I do as a way of managing the fact that I couldn't help but welcome them and open the door for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So,
[SPEAKER_01]: Not welcoming them does not equal denying them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It simply equals not welcoming them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if they remain sitting in your face for as long as they want.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Learning how to sustain that yoniso manasikāra, the right way of attending to them, as if you are not welcome, regardless of everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then they'll stop coming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, yeah, you truly obliterated them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Destroyed them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Surpassed them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, they're not coming up anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: Factually.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're gone.
[SPEAKER_03]: Would you say this is the... the definition... the difference between... it's a mind or the definition in the suttas that you read about quite often, limited and unlimited.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, your mind is limited by this...
[SPEAKER_03]: Ill-will.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now, it is not limited by that thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not bound to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, well, yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: There would be, there would be like a different degrees of limit as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, see, once this, once this becomes more and more apparent, through being rightly restrained, rightly established in your precepts, in your speech, then you start to recognize that the deliberate welcoming of thoughts, obviously, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: As I said, it's not going to be perfect overnight.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might not do it, but then you might do a little bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to the extent that you allow it, to take the center stage, to the center you welcome it, to that extent you're limited.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you might be less limited than before, but if there is the slightest extent of welcoming such thoughts,
[SPEAKER_01]: So, to that extent, there is a limit.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you truly, then, mind is completely free from slightest degree of welcoming those thoughts, your mind is unlimited.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's basically when you are surmounted the five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the ill will is not limiting you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You deliberately allowing it to take the center stage is the limit.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what limits it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what narrows it down.